# 青海·西宁
Xining, Qinghai Province
# 西宁市 是青藏高原的东方门户
Xining city is the eastern gate of the Qinghai-Tibet plateau
# 独特的气候条件 和 地理条件
It has unique climate and geographical conditions
# 使得这边形成了丰富的饮食文化
in which the rich food culture here has been formed
# 在众多的美食当中
Among all the great food around
# 羊肉应该是出镜率最高的美食了
Lamb appears the most
# 今天呢在西宁 我们找一个羊肉的特色吃法
Today in Xining, we’re going to try a special style of lamb
# 手抓羊肉
"Shou Zhua Yang Rou" (lit. Hand-grabbing boiled lamb)
# 就是这里了
Right here
# 一个个师傅都是抱着一怀的羊肉走进后厨
All the cooks are having lamb full in their arms when they walk in the kitchen
# 从路过的场面能够看出
We can see from here
# 他们好像抱的都是肋排 羊排 还有羊腿
They are holding lamb ribs and legs
# 这样的肉多一些
Mostly ribs and legs
*Raw Meat*
# 不知道自己说的对不对呢 待会去验证一下
I don’t know if I’m right. Let’s find out later
# 哇
Whoa
*Raw Meat*
# 又来了一个
Another bunch (pile)
# 咱们原来看剁肉的 都是在案板上
Usually we cut meat on a chopping board
# 我刚才发现他们这边剁肉 有点不同
I just found out their way of chopping is a bit different
# 他们的案板好像特别高
They have an extra high chopping board
# 看来刚才的羊肉还只是冰山一角
All the lamb we saw are just the tip of the iceberg
# 我不断地录 他们这边羊肉不断地放
They kept laying down lamb as I was shooting
# 现在羊肉堆的 就像一座大山
All the lamb here looks like a mountain now
# 虽然说 这边是一个饭店
It is a restaurant
# 但是我觉得它更像是一个手抓羊肉的加工厂
But I think it’s more like a boiled lamb factory
# 这边的羊肉剁完就会在另一边清洗
First they chop the lamb and wash it on the other side
# 清洗之后 （羊肉）要炸 要焖
Then they fry and boil the lamb
# 整个的制作过程可能需要十多个人来参与
The whole process needs more than a dozen people
# 两个多小时才能够忙完 特别忙碌
It takes more than two hours and everybody is so busy
# 因为肉太多 而且锅很大
The amount of lamb is huge and they have a tremendous pot
# 所以说 在放羊肉的时候
So, when they put the lamb in the pot
# 需要在下面放上一层料包
They need to put a layer of seasoning bags at the bottom
# 上面再放一层料包 这样羊肉才能够更加入味
And another layer of seasoning bags on the top so that the flavor can penetrate
# 现在羊肉呢 是正在炖着
Now the lamb is being boiled
# 厨师们正在吃饭
The cooks are having their meals
# 我发现他们吃的东西 我是没见过的
I found out that they are eating something I’ve never seen
# 你好 我问一下 这个叫什么
Hi excuse me, what’s this?
# 这个叫焜锅馍馍
It’s "Kun Guo Mo Mo" (lit. stew pot bun)
# 原来它就是焜锅馍馍
Oh this is "Dun Guo Mo Mo"
# 啊 它还有一个名字
Yeah, and it has another name
# 青海面包
Qinghai bread
# 它是甜的吗 还是说 只是面粉的味道
- Is it sweet? Or is it just the taste of flour?
- Only the taste of flour
# 很自然的 没有添加的
It‘s made from natural ingredients and we didn't add in any extra additives
# 像在我们那儿 馍馍都是蒸出来的
In our place the buns are steamed
# 我发现这个馍馍是烤出来的
This bun was baked
# 逮住老板 问几个问题
We got the owner to ask a few questions
# 我想问一下 我看羊肉不是全羊
I want to ask whether the mutton is from a whole lamb
# 是羊的前身
It’s the fore half of the sheep
# 就是后腿部分不要的
We don’t have the hind legs
# 后腿部分 一般要的比较少一些
The hind legs don’t get ordered that much
# 要后腿主要是为了炒菜用
They are mainly for stir-frying dishes
# 做黄焖手抓羊肉 主要用的是羊的前身
We mainly use the fore half for boiled lamb or stewed lamb
# 羊的前身 就是
The fore half are basically
# 羊脖子 羊腱子那些 羊排 软肋这些都要的
The neck, fore shank, ribs and loin. All of them
# 羊一般是多大的羊
How old are the sheep usually?
# 这个羊就是六七个月 半岁吧 半岁多
They are about 6-7 months. A little over half-year old
# 也就这么个样子
That’s about it
# 得多重
How much do they usually weigh?
# 我们家一般是自己亲自去选 在羊肉铺
We usually go to the butcher’s ourselves
# 大小在30斤左右
The sheep is about 30 jins (1 jin=500 g)
# 这样就是一锅能煮出来
So the lamb in the whole pot can be evenly cooked
# 要是大小有差异的话 一锅煮出来
If the size of lamb differ too much and we cook them in one pot
# 硬的硬 糯的糯 就是不太合适
The texture will differ from tough and soft. That won’t be appropriate
# 这样煮出来的话 肥而不腻
The half-year old sheep after cooking is rich but not greasy
# 出锅后会香嫩一些
After boiling, it will have an aroma and a soft, juicy texture
# 这里的羊肉真的是特别多 剁好的羊肉都有30多盆
It has the world’s lamb here. The chopped lamb alone fills more than 30 pots
# 一天能够做多少斤的羊肉
How many jins of lamb can we make here a day?
# 大概就是三百多斤吧 四百斤左右
More than 300 jins (1 jin=500 g). About 400 jins.
# 看到捞羊肉的场景 只能用壮观来形容了
It’s such a view to watch them get the lamb out of the pot
# 来吧 吃羊肉吧
Alright, let’s try some lamb
# 哇 好香啊
Whoa! It smells so good
# 这就是我们点的手抓羊肉
This is the boiled lamb we ordered
# 这个要蘸着辣酱吃是吧
Does it go with the hot sauce?
# 嗯对
Yeah right
# 现在手抓羊肉的料已经齐全了
Now we have all the dippings for the lamb
# 一份这个是带点辣椒油的
This one has some chili oil
# 油碟吧 然后这个就是椒盐
The oil dipping. And this is the spiced salt
# 刚才 我弱智地问了一句 这个怎么吃
I just asked a stupid question on how to have these
# 她说 撒上去吃也行 然后蘸着吃也行
She told me to either spread them on the meat or dip the meat in
# 羊肉 一定要手抓着吃
It’s important that we use our hands to eat the lamb
# 这样吃 才有特色
That’s the style
# 你看 咱们在新疆吃手抓饭
Remember we had pilaf in Xijiang?
# 虽然叫手抓饭 但是可以用勺 筷子来吃
Even though it’s called hand grabbing rice, we usually have it with a spoon or chopsticks
# 今天这份手抓羊肉
Today we are having the boiled lamb, which is called hand grabbing lamb
# 是真的要用手抓着吃
We are actually gonna grab them with our hands
# 吃这个
To have it
# 就趁热吃
Let’s try when it’s still hot
# 先吃原味的
Let’s try the original taste first
# 它这个肉 炖的特别烂
The texture is really soft after boiling
# 吃起来毫不费力
Doesn’t need any effort for you to eat them
# 可以蘸辣酱吃 也可以蘸干碟吃
You can also have it with the hot sauce or the spiced salt
# 辣酱）它也不是很辣
The hot sauce is not that spicy
# 这个是我们自己配制的蒜酱
It’s the homemade garlic sauce
# 蒜和辣子的调料
Garlic and chili sauce
# 刚才是蘸的油碟 它是里面有油 有蒜汁的
We just tried the chili oil. It has chili oil and garlic sauce
# 咱们现在蘸下干的
Now let’s try the spiced salt
# 它就是另外一种风味
It’s a different flavor
# 就是没有油 没有蒜汁的味道
It doesn’t have the oil or the garlic flavor
# 反而有点烧烤的意思
It’s more like barbecue
# 在西宁这边吃羊肉 可能就不能那么约束
When you have lamb in Xining, don’t restrict yourself
# 需要粗犷一点
You can be more rugged
# 中午伴随我的除了羊肉 还有想了很久的酸奶
Besides the lamb, my lunch also has the yogurt which I’ve been looking forward for a long time
# 上面有很黄的一层 但不是奶皮
It has a yellow layer but it’s not the milk skin
# 老板说是加了当地的食用油 这样颜色会更好看一些
The owner told me they added some local vegetable oil so it has a better color
# 还有就是麦仁粥 小小的一碗 里面却有丰富的材料
Also there’s the wheat congee. It has a lot of ingredients in a small bowl
# 它里面真的能看到小麦 黄豆
We can see the wheat and beans here
# 还冒着热气呢
It’s still steaming
# 这里面是加了胡椒粉吗
Is it pepper in there?
# 对
Yeah
# 还有肉
And also meat
# 是加了一些牛肉
Some beef
# 最后 我还得提一下我眼前的这盘土豆
Last, I need to mention the plate of potatoes here
# 外面脆 里面是有点绵 有点软
Crunchy outside and smooth inside